{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Which of the following is an undesirable dynamic characteristic of an instrument ?", "opta": "Reproducibility", "optb": "Dead zone", "optc": "Time lag", "optd": "Static error", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not the triple point of water ?", "opta": "32\u00b0R", "optb": "273\u00b0K", "optc": "492\u00b0R", "optd": "32\u00b0F", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the one which is a first order instrument.", "opta": "Mercury in glass thermometer (without any covering or air gap).", "optb": "Bare metallic thermometer.", "optc": "Bare vapor pressure thermometer.", "optd": "All (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Load cells are used for the measurement of", "opta": "stress", "optb": "weight", "optc": "strain", "optd": "velocity", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the dynamic characteristics of an instrument ?", "opta": "Reproducibility", "optb": "Sensitivity", "optc": "Dead zone", "optd": "Fidelity", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "O2, NO and NO2 exhibit paramagnetic properties as a result of unpaired electrons.", "optb": "CO2 is the strongest paramagnetic gas.", "optc": "Paramagnetic susceptibility of gases decreases with temperature.", "optd": "Paramagnetic susceptibility of gases permits the measurement of their concentration.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The __________ of a vapor pressure thermometer is a functioning element.", "opta": "pointer", "optb": "bourdon tube", "optc": "bulb", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A negative gain margin expressed in decibels means a/an __________ system.", "opta": "stable", "optb": "unstable", "optc": "critically damped", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermistor, which has high temperature co-efficient of resistivity, is used as the sensing element in resistance thermometer. It is a/an", "opta": "insulator", "optb": "conductor", "optc": "solid semi-conductor", "optd": "liquid semi-conductor", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Flapper nozzle is used in a/an __________ controller.", "opta": "electronic", "optb": "hydraulic", "optc": "pneumatic", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Typical specifications for design stipulates the gain margin and phase margin to be respectively", "opta": "> 1.7 and > 30\u00b0", "optb": "< 1.7 and  > 30\u00b0", "optc": "< 1.7 and < 30\u00b0", "optd": "> 1.7 and < 30\u00b0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Working principle of radiation pyrometer is based on the", "opta": "Wien's law", "optb": "Kirchoffs law", "optc": "Stafan-Boltzman law", "optd": "Seebeck effect", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following relates the emf. generated in a single homogeneous wire to the temperature difference ?", "opta": "Peltier effect", "optb": "Thomson effect", "optc": "Seebeck effect", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dilute wine was used as a thermometric liquid initially to develop temperature scale. First emperical temperature scale developed was the __________ scale.", "opta": "Kelvin", "optb": "Centigrade", "optc": "Fahrenheit", "optd": "Reaumer", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a single tank system, the transfer function of level to inlet flow rate is", "opta": "R/TS", "optb": "R/(TS + 1)", "optc": "l(TS + l)", "optd": "1/TS", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is a desirable characteristic of an instrument ?", "opta": "High drift", "optb": "High fidelity", "optc": "High measuring lag", "optd": "Poor reproducibility", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The operation of a rotameter is based on", "opta": "variable flow area.", "optb": "rotation of a turbine.", "optc": "pressure drop across a nozzle.", "optd": "pressure at a stagnation point.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The temperature of tempering oil baths maintained at 400\u00b0C during heat treatment of steel is measured by a/an __________ thermocouple.", "opta": "chromel-alumel", "optb": "iron-constantan", "optc": "platinum-platinum/rhodium", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Instrumentation in a plant offers the advantage of", "opta": "greater safety of operation", "optb": "better quality of product", "optc": "greater operation economy", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following temperature measuring instruments need not touch the object whose temperature is being measured ?", "opta": "Radiation/infrared pyrometer", "optb": "Filled system thermometer", "optc": "Mercury in glass thermometer", "optd": "Thermo electric pyrometer", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermal conductivity measurement com-prises the working principle of a", "opta": "CO2 analyser", "optb": "polarimeter", "optc": "spectrometer", "optd": "chromatograph", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Response of a system to a sinusoidal input is called __________ response.", "opta": "impluse", "optb": "unit step", "optc": "frequency", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The closed loop pole of a stable second order system could be", "opta": "both real and positive.", "optb": "complex conjugate with positive real parts.", "optc": "both real and negative.", "optd": "one real positive and the other real negative.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Smoke density of the flue gas going out of the chimney is measured by a", "opta": "polarograph", "optb": "thermal conductivity meter", "optc": "photo electric cell", "optd": "chromatograph", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Transfer function of transportation lag is", "opta": "eTS", "optb": "e-TS", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Temperature measuring instruments are standardised mostly with __________ points of pure substances.", "opta": "melting", "optb": "boiling", "optc": "both (a) & (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the first order system from among the following.", "opta": "Damped vibrator.", "optb": "Mercury in glass thermometer kept in boiling water.", "optc": "Interacting system of two tanks in series.", "optd": "Non-interacting system of two tanks in series.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum service temperature for fibre glass used as thermocouple wire insulation material is __________ \u00b0C.", "opta": "250", "optb": "500", "optc": "750", "optd": "1000", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following controllers has the least maximum deviation ?", "opta": "P-controller", "optb": "P-I controller", "optc": "P-I-D controller", "optd": "P-D controller", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Volumetric expansion is the working principle of the __________ thermometers.", "opta": "mercury in glass", "optb": "constant volume gas", "optc": "vapor pressure", "optd": "bimetallic", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following measurements can be made by the measurement of emf ?", "opta": "pH value", "optb": "Degree of hydrolysis", "optc": "Composition of complex ions", "optd": "All (a), (b) & (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A magnetic flowmeter is", "opta": "based on the principle of Faraday's law.", "optb": "capable of measuring the flow rate of slurries and electrolytes.", "optc": "based on the linear relationship between the fluid flow rate and the induced voltage.", "optd": "all (a), (b) and (c).", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Zirconia probe is used for the continuous measurment of __________ flue gases going out of the furnace.", "opta": "oxygen in", "optb": "carbon dioxide in", "optc": "carbon monoxide in", "optd": "temperature of", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Strain gage pressure transducers are used to measure __________ pressures.", "opta": "gage as well as vacuum", "optb": "absolute as well as differential", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The transfer function for a PID controller is (where, \u03c4 i is the integral (reset) time and \u03c4D is the derivative time.)", "opta": "Kc(1 + \u03c4is + \u03c4D ). s", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Compositional analysis of __________ is done using mass spectrometer.", "opta": "an isotope", "optb": "natural gas", "optc": "a solid", "optd": "an alloy", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The function of a transducer is to", "opta": "modify the input signal.", "optb": "amplify the input signal.", "optc": "convert the primary signal into a more useful quantity, usually an electric impulse.", "optd": "codify/decodify the input signal.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nichol's chart deals with", "opta": "A.R. vs. phase lag of first order.", "optb": "A.R. vs. phase lag of second order.", "optc": "closed loop values vs. open loop values.", "optd": "frequency response values of controllers.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following thermocouples will give the highest output for the same value of hot and cold junction temperature ?", "opta": "Platinum-platinum + rhodium.", "optb": "Iron-constantan.", "optc": "Chromel-constantan.", "optd": "All will give the same output.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A proportional controller with a gain of Kc is used to control a first order process. The offset will increase, if", "opta": "Kc is reduced.", "optb": "Kc is increased.", "optc": "integral control action is introduced.", "optd": "derivative control action is introduced.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The symbol for \"capillary line\" in instrumentation diagram is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ is undesirable in thermocouples used in industries,", "opta": "Linear relation of emf to temperature", "optb": "Corrosion resistance", "optc": "Oxidation resistance", "optd": "Non-linear relation of emf to temperature", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Select the correct statement from the following.", "opta": "The frequency response of a pure capacity process is unbounded.", "optb": "The phase lag of a pure time delay system decreases with increasing frequency.", "optc": "The amplitude ratio of a pure capacity process is inversely proportional to frequency.", "optd": "The amplitude ratio of a pure time delay system increases with frequency.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For an input forcing function, X(t) = 2t2, the Laplace transform of this function is", "opta": "2/s2", "optb": "4/s2", "optc": "2/s3", "optd": "4/s3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Continuous shell temperature measurement in a liquid-liquid heat exchanger is done by a", "opta": "thermocouple", "optb": "reistance thermometer", "optc": "mercury in glass thermometer", "optd": "vapor pressure thermometer", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The __________ of a vapor pressure thermometer is a secondary element.", "opta": "pointer", "optb": "Bourdon tube", "optc": "bulb", "optd": "none ofthese", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Emf developed by a thermocouple, while measuring a temperature of 600\u00b0C is about 5.5 mV. The type of thermocouple used is", "opta": "chromel-alumel", "optb": "iron-constantan", "optc": "platinum-platinum+rhodium", "optd": "either (a), (b) or (c)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following relates the absorption & evolution of heat at the junctions of a thermocouple to the current flow in the circuit?", "opta": "Seebeck effect", "optb": "Peltier effect", "optc": "Joule heating effect", "optd": "Thomson effect", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The second order system with the transfer function  has a damping ratio of", "opta": "2.0", "optb": "0.5", "optc": "1.0", "optd": "4.0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a shell and tube heat exchanger, the flow rate of heating/cooling fluid is the __________ variable.", "opta": "load", "optb": "controlled", "optc": "manipulated", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}